Douglas Southall Freeman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Speech, Article, and Book File, 1908-1954 (Box 126-169)
  - Books (Box 131)
    - Lee of Virginia
      - Notes on the account of the opening of “Pickett's Charge”
      - Chapters 40-41
      - Chapters 40-53, (6 folders) (Box 134)
      - Chapters 54-65, (6 folders) (Box 135)
      - Chapters 65-76, (7 folders) (Box 136)
      - Chapters 77-97, (8 folders) (Box 137)
      - Chapters 98-127, (7 folders) (Box 138)
      - Appendix
      - Bibliography, index and miscellaneous (Box 139)
      - Bibliography, (2 folders)
      - Index
      - Corrections
      - Miscellaneous, (5 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, (9 folders) (Box 140)
      - Miscellaneous and maps, (5 folders) (Box 141)
      - Introduction, Chapter 3 (Box 142)
      - Earliest manuscript
      - Characters in the book
      - Principal manuscript sources
      - Notes, etc., for typist
      - Foreword, (2 folders)
      - Introduction, (2 folders)
      - Style sheets
      - Chapters 1-3, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous pages from chapters 1-21
      - Chapters 4-12, (9 folders) (Box 143)
      - Chapters 12-21, (7 folders) (Box 144)
      - Chapters 20-28, (9 folders) (Box 145)
      - Chapters 28-36, (11 folders) (Box 146)
      - Chapters 36-50, (13 folders) (Box 147)
      - Chapters 50-62, (12 folders) (Box 148)
      - Chapters 62-80, (14 folders) (Box 149)
      - Chapters 81-end and miscellaneous (Box 150)
        - Virginia insurgency, 1896-1917
        - Arlington edition (insert material)
        - Chapters 81-84
        - Appendix, (3 folders)
        - Miscellaneous
      - Printer's copy I, pages 1-555, (3 folders) (Box 151)
      - Printer's copy II (Box 152)
        - Pages 26-482, (2 folders)
        - Pages 905-1047
      - Printer's copy III (Box 153)
        - Pages 1048-1160
        - Pages 556-1007, (2 folders)
      - Printer's copy IV, pages 1008-(?) (Box 154)
    - South to Posterity (Box 155)
      - Miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - “On the Road to Appomattox”, (2 folders)
      - “The Last Bivovacs”
      - List of West Point cadets and war relationships to Robert E. Lee
    - Washington (Box 156)
      - Vol. I
        - Style sheet for Washington
        - Washington introduction
        - Chapters 1-3, (8 folders)
        - Chapters 4-5, (2 folders) (Box 157)
        - Chapters 7-12, (6 folders)
        - Appendix 3
        - Appendices 9-10, (2 folders)
        - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
        - I and II notes for reviewers and manuscript sources
        - II text from illustrations
      - Vol. II (Box 158)
        - Chapter 1
        - Chapters 8-20, (20 folders)
        - Appendix, (2 folders)
      - Vol. III (Box 159)
        - Vols. II and III, miscellaneous
        - Vols. III and IV, short title index
        - Chapter 1
        - Vols. III and IV, introduction
        - Chapters 2-12, (11 folders)
        - Chapters 13-16, (5 folders) (Box 160)
        - Chapters 18-21, (4 folders)
        - Chapter 23
        - Appendix
        - Miscellaneous
      - Vol. IV (Box 161)
        - Chapters 1-6, (9 folders)
        - Chapters 8-10, (3 folders)
        - Chapters 12-13, (2 folders)
        - Chapters 14-22, (9 folders) (Box 162)
        - Chapter 24
        - Appendix
        - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
        - General biographical note
        - Memorandum for reviewers for vols. III and IV
      - Vol. V (Box 163)
        - Introduction
        - Chapters 1-10, (8 folders)
        - Chapters 11-17, (10 folders) (Box 164)
        - Chapters 18-24, (8 folders) (Box 165)
        - Chapters 24-29, (6 folders) (Box 166)
        - Miscellaneous, (3 folders)
      - Vol. VI (Box 167)
        - Page on Freeman's writing board when he died, 1953 June 13
        - Chapters 1-11, (16 folders)
        - Chapter 13
        - Chapter 12 (Box 168)
        - Chapters 14-16, (3 folders)
        - Parts of the outline for Washington
        - Miscellaneous, (3 folders)
        - Work proofs (Box 169)
          - Miscellaneous
          - Page proofs, etc., (4 folders)
- Research File, 1908-1954 (Box 170-209)
  Source material, including transcripts, photostats, notes, and maps, and miscellaneous bibliographical material.
  Arranged generally as compiled by Freeman.
  - Revolutionary period copies of sources, miscellaneous notes for Washington, (2 folders) (Box 170)
  - Civil War sources and photstats (Box 171)
    - Vol. I, (5 folders)
    - Vol. II, (9 folders) (Box 172)
    - Vol. III, (5 folders) (Box 173)
    - Miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 174)
    - Source material on First Virginia Infantry Organization (Box 175)
  - Minutes, etc., of Current Events Club (Box 176)
    - Vol. I, 1925-1934, (10 folders)
    - Vol. II, 1918 Sept.-1924, Oct., (5 folders) (Box 177)
    - Volume III (Box 178)
      - 1926 Sept.-1928., Nov., (2 folders)
      - Correspondence, 1920-1925
      - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
  - Manuscripts by others (Box 179)
    - McCabe, W. Gordon, “Major Venable.. .”
    - Ecxenrode, H. J., Lee...
    - “A Night on Furlough” (?)
    - Weber, C. H., speech in Richmond, 1913 Nov. 12
    - Carlrow, Charles J., “Battle at Chaffin's Farm,” 1932
    - Durkin, Joseph T., “Stephen Russell Mallory”
  - Washington (Box 180)
    - Notebook I, long sheets, (4 notebooks)
    - Notebook II, long sheets, (4 notebooks) (Box 181)
    - Notebook III, miscellaneous, (4 notebooks) (Box 182)
    - Notebook IV, miscellaneous, (4 notebooks) (Box 183)
    - Notebook V, miscellaneous, (4 notebooks) (Box 184)
    - Notebook VI, miscellaneous, (4 notebooks) (Box 185)
    - Notebook VII, miscellaneous, (4 notebooks) (Box 186)
    - Notes I, (2 stacks) (Box 187)
    - Notes II, (2 stacks) (Box 188)
    - Notes III, (2 stacks) (Box 189)
    - Notes IV, (2 stacks) (Box 190)
    - Notes V, (2 stacks) (Box 191, Box 192)
    - Notes VII, (2 stacks) (Box 193)
    - Notes VIII, (2 stacks) (Box 194)
    - Notes IX, (3 stacks) (Box 195)
    - Notes X, (3 stacks) (Box 196)
    - Notes XI, (3 stacks) (Box 197)
    - Notes and bibliography I, (3 stacks) (Box 198)
    - Notes and bibliography II, (3 stacks) (Box 199)
    - Notes and bibliography III, (3 stacks) (Box 200)
    - Notes and bibliography IV, (3 stacks) (Box 201)
    - Notes and bibliography V, (3 stacks) (Box 202)
    - Notes and bibliography VI, (3 stacks) (Box 203)
    - Notes and bibliography VII, (3 stacks) (Box 204)
    - Notes and bibliography VIII, (3 stacks) (Box 205)
    - Notes and bibliography IX, (3 stacks) (Box 206)
    - Notes and bibliography X, (3 stacks) (Box 207)
    - Notes and bibliography XI, (3 stacks) (Box 208)
    - Notes and bibliography XII, (3 stacks) (Box 209)
- Miscellany, 1907-1954 (Box 210-238)
  Newspaper clippings, programs, photographs, printed matter, and memorabilia.
  Grouped by type of material but otherwise unarranged.
  - Clippings, (2 scrapbooks); (2 folders); (3 letter stacks) (Box 210, Box 211, Box 212, Box 213, Box 214, Box 215, Box 216, Box 217, Box 218, Box 219, Box 220, Box 221, Box 222)
  - Diplomas, (2 folders) (Box 223)
  - Photographs, (3 folders); (13 folders) (Box 224, Box 225)
  - Programs, etc., (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 226, Box 227)
  - Maps, (2 folders) (Box 228)
  - Volume of Lee's Lieutenants burned on a plane and an autographed military encyclopedia of Italy, 1943-1945 (Box 229)
  - Printed matter (Box 230)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Pamphlets
      - Pamphlets and books (Box 231)
      - Pamphlet and book (Box 232)
      - Pamphlets and book (Box 233)
      - Pamphlets (Box 234)
      - Pamphlets (Box 235)
  - General material See Oversize, (4 folders); (4 packets); (3 folders) (Box 236, Box 237, Box 238)
- Addition, 1917-1979 (Box 239-242)
  General correspondence, speeches and writings, printed matter, and miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - General correspondence (Box 239)
    - 1917
    - 1923
    - 1936
    - 1938
    - 1942, 1944-1947
    - 1948-1979, (32 folders)
    - Undated
  - Speeches and writings (Box 240)
    - An insight to the life of Freeman
    - Illustrations and portraits in books
    - Freeman markers, 1968
    - Jefferson Davis unveiling, 1952
    - Lee, Robert E., (3 folders)
    - Washington, George
  - Freeman's books (5 books) (Box 241)
  - General miscellany (Box 242)
    - Civil War Round Table citation
    - Miscellaneous data on West Point graduates
    - In memoriam of Freeman
    - Memorandum of conversation with David Lloyd George, 1923
    - Birthday greetings
    - Announcements
    - Citation to accompany the Bronze Star Award, 1944
    - Directions for Freeman's funeral, 1953 June 10
    - Plan for formal garden, 1938
- Oversize (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Photographs, diplomas, and maps.
  Described according to the series and container from which the material was removed.
  - Miscellany (Container 238) (Box OV 1)
    - General
      - Maps, pictures
      - Diplomas (Box OV 2)